Guide to the Vern Haugland Papers 1908-1987
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Writings, 1942-1983; Series II; 3.75 linear feet
  - Subseries 1: Manuscripts
    - "The World's not so Damned Big, After All", undated (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Subseries 2: Datelines
    - Apollo 9, undated (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Apollo 12, 13, 14, 1970, undated (Box-folder 10/7)
    - Apollo 13, 1970 (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Apollo 15, undated (Box-folder 10/9)
    - Apollo Space Crews, 1960 (Box-folder 10/10)
    - Astronaut Communication, undated (Box-folder 10/11)
    - Auto-Train, undated (Box-folder 10/12)
    - Awards, Vern Haugland, undated (Box-folder 10/13)
    - B-29, 1945 (Box-folder 10/14)
    - Bomber Flight, undated (Box-folder 10/15)
    - CAB, 1967 (Box-folder 10/16)
    - Carpenter Flight, undated (Box-folder 10/17)
    - Enterprise Carrier, undated (Box-folder 10/18)
    - Frogman Killed in Vietnam, 1970 (Box-folder 10/19)
    - Gemini 4, undated (Box-folder 10/20)
    - Gemini 9, 1966 (Box-folder 10/21)
    - Gemini 9, 1966 (Box-folder 10/22)
    - German Shepherds for Airport Security, 1972 (Box-folder 10/23)
    - Haiti Lift Ban on Military Flights, undated (Box-folder 10/24)
    - Hijacking, undated (Box-folder 10/25)
    - Hiroshima, 1945 (Box-folder 10/26)
    - Hobby-plane, 1972 (Box-folder 10/27)
    - Indonesia, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 10/28)
    - Java, 1945 (Box-folder 10/29)
    - Korea, undated (Box-folder 10/30)
    - Seven Mercury Astronauts, 1959 (Box-folder 10/31)
    - Flight Service to Mexico, 1960 (Box-folder 10/32)
    - Missile Ships, undated (Box-folder 10/33)
    - Naval Research Lab, undated (Box-folder 10/34)
    - Plane Crash, 1972 (Box-folder 10/35)
    - Russia, 1956 (Box-folder 10/36)
    - Russia, 1959 (Box-folder 10/37)
    - Soviet Missiles, 1962 (Box-folder 10/38)
    - Spanish AP Dateline, 1972 (Box-folder 10/39)
    - Sumatra, 1945 (Box-folder 10/40)
    - Supersonic Flight, undated (Box-folder 10/41)
    - USS Enterprise, 1962 (Box-folder 10/42)
    - USS Enterprise, 1962 (Box-folder 10/43)
    - USS Enterprise, 1962 (Box-folder 10/44)
    - USS Essex, Apollo 7, undated (Box-folder 10/45)
    - USS Guadalcanal, Apollo 9, undated (Box-folder 10/46)
    - USS Guadalcanal, 1969 (Box-folder 10/47)
    - USS Intrepid, undated (Box-folder 10/48)
    - USS New Orleans, Skylab, 1974 (Box-folder 10/49)
    - USS New Orleans, Skylab 3, undated (Box-folder 10/50)
    - USS New Orleans, 1975 (Box-folder 10/51)
    - USS Okinawa, 1971 (Box-folder 10/52)
    - USS Okinawa, Apollo 15, 1971 (Box-folder 10/53)
    - USS Ticonderoga, 1972 (Box-folder 11/1)
    - USS Ticonderoga, 1972 (Box-folder 11/2)
    - USS Wasp, 1965 (Box-folder 11/3)
    - USS Wasp, Gemini, undated (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Vanguard, 1957 (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Vanguard I, 2nd Anniversary, undated (Box-folder 11/6)
    - Vanguard Reunion, 1968 (Box-folder 11/7)
    - Vanguard I, 1973 (Box-folder 11/8)
    - Wright's Recipes, 1978 (Box-folder 11/9)
    - Major General Yates, 1959 (Box-folder 11/10)
    - The AAF Against Japan, galley proofs, 1948 (Box-folder OS 1/1)
    - Revolt in Paradise, galley proofs, 1960 (Box-folder OS 1/2)
- Financial Records, 1938-1981; Series III; 29 folders
  The series contains general and travel receipts from the many locations in which Haugland traveled to for the Associated Press. Also in the series are his expense accounts and tax information, including tax returns. The series is arranged in two parts. The first part, general financial records, is arranged chronologically.
  The second part is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - 1938-1941 (Box-folder 11/11)
  - 1942-1944 (Box-folder 11/12)
  - 1945 (Box-folder 11/13)
  - 1947 (Box-folder 11/14)
  - 1948 (Box-folder 11/15)
  - 1950 (Box-folder 11/16)
  - 1952-1957 (Box-folder 11/17)
  - 1969-1971 (Box-folder 11/18)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 11/19)
  - 1981 (Box-folder 11/20)
  - Apartment Rental, 1965 (Box-folder 11/21)
  - Book Sale, 1948 (Box-folder 11/22)
  - Expense Accounts, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 11/23)
  - Expense Account, 1956 (Box-folder 11/24)
  - Expense Account, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 11/25)
  - Expense Accounts for Recovery Assignment, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 11/26)
  - Hawaii, 1970 (Box-folder 11/27)
  - Hawaii, 1971 (Box-folder 11/28)
  - Rome Trip, 1957 (Box-folder 11/29)
  - Royal Crescent Hotel, 1976 (Box-folder 11/30)
  - Strike Benefit Checks, 1969 (Box-folder 11/31)
  - Tax Information, 1943 (Box-folder 11/32)
  - Tax Information, 1946 (Box-folder 11/33)
  - Taxes, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 11/34)
  - Tax Returns, 1949-1953 (Box-folder 11/35)
  - K'tut Tantri, 1959 (Box-folder 11/36)
  - USS Okinawa Receipt, 1971 (Box-folder 11/37)
  - War Years, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 11/38)
  - Ziff-Davis Advance, 1978 (Box-folder 11/39)
- Legal Documents, 1942-1977; Series IV; 12 folders
  The series consists mainly of documents from Haugland's years as a war correspondent. They include his license, passports, war correspondent agreement contract, orders, a permit to leave the United States, and an Australian registration. Other documents in the series are agreements with publishing companies for Haugland's manuscripts, such as Harper and Brothers and Spartan Books.
  The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Agreement, Harper and Brothers, 1945 (Box-folder 11/41)
  - Agreement for War Correspondents, 1944 (Box-folder 11/42)
  - Australian Registration, 1942 (Box-folder 11/43)
  - Contract for the publication of "Big Men of the Sky", 1955 (Box-folder 11/44)
  - Contract with Spartan Books, 1965, 1967 (Box-folder 11/45)
  - Ficha do Turista, 1957 (Box-folder 11/46)
  - Movement of Accredited War Correspondents, Australia, undated (Box-folder 11/47)
  - Orders for War Correspondent, 1943 (Box-folder 11/48)
  - Passports, 1953-1977 (Box-folder 11/49)
  - Permit of Local Board to Deport United States, 1943 (Box-folder 11/50)
  - Release Form for Manuscript, 1976 (Box-folder 11/51)
  - War Correspondent License and Identification Card, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 11/52)
- Research Materials, 1943-1987, undated; Series V; 1.75 linear feet
  The series contains materials that Haugland used in research for his articles. The majority of research materials are about NASA and the space program. Haugland covered the Apollo missions, Gemini and Voyager. Other topics that Haugland researched were the places he traveled, military, and K'tut Tantri in Indonesia. He also collected numerous materials on the Eagle squadrons, the American pilots who flew for the British during WWII.
  - Airplane, DC7 Inaugural Flight, 1953 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Associated Press, AP Log, 1977 (Box-folder 12/2)
  - Associated Press, "A Newsletter for AP Graduates", 1974, 1977 (Box-folder 12/3)
  - Concorde, 1976 (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Dutch Treat Club West Meeting, 1983 (Box-folder 12/5)
  - Eagles, Address List, 1987 (Box-folder 12/6)
  - Eagles, American Eagles, undated (Box-folder 12/7)
  - Eagles, "The Day a Squadron was Lost", undated (Box-folder 12/8)
  - Eagles, Eagle Pilots Recall, 1980 (Box-folder 12/9)
  - Eagles, Eagle Squadron Association News, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 12/10)
  - Eagles, Eagle Squadron Association, 1985 (Box-folder 12/11)
  - Eagles, Information for Book, 1943, 1976, undated (Box-folder 12/12)
  - Eagles, Letter to the Queen of England, 1976 (Box-folder 12/13)
  - "A Man for All Wars", 1982 (Box-folder 12/14)
  - Eagles, Maps, undated (Box-folder 12/15)
  - Eagles, Media Distribution List, 1979 (Box-folder 12/16)
  - Eagles, Memorial Dedication, 1986 (Box-folder 12/17)
  - Eagles, Memorial Unveiling, 1986 (Box-folder 12/18)
  - Eagles, Newsletter, 1974-1982 (Box-folder 12/19)
  - Eagles, Operation Jubilee, undated (Box-folder 12/20)
  - Eagles, Photos for The Eagle's War, undated (Box-folder 12/21)
  - Eagles, Pinnacle Books' Report, 1978 (Box-folder 12/22)
  - Eagles, Poem, undated (Box-folder 12/23)
  - Eagles, Reunions, 1976, 1979 (Box-folder 12/24)
  - Eagles, Reviews, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 12/25)
  - Eagles, Review of The Eagle Squadrons, 1979 (Box-folder 12/26)
  - Eagles, Traveler, 1986 (Box-folder 12/27)
  - Eagles, "Veterans Relive Wartime Flying", 1979 (Box-folder 12/28)
  - Eagles, War Memorial Story, undated (Box-folder 12/29)
  - Eagles, Ziff-Davis Author's Questionaire, undated (Box-folder 12/30)
  - Indonesia, Revolt in Paradise research, 1946, undated (Box-folder 12/31)
  - Indonesia, Soedarno during the war, undated (Box-folder 12/32)
  - General Curtis E. LeMay, non-stop flight to Argentina, undated (Box-folder 12/33)
  - Lt. Colonel Frank McCoy, citation for Legion of Merit, undated (Box-folder 12/34)
  - Military, Air Force Missile Test Center, undated (Box-folder 12/35)
  - Military, B-47, undated (Box-folder 12/36)
  - Military, C-5 Trip, 1972 (Box-folder 12/37)
  - Military, F-14 Tomcat, 1973-1974, 1976 (Box-folder 12/38)
  - Military, "I Flew with the Stratojets," Wesley Price, 1953 (Box-folder 12/39)
  - Military, Travel Orders, 1945 (Box-folder 12/40)
  - Military, The 22 nd Newsletter, 1964 (Box-folder 12/41)
  - Military, Q and A, USAF, 1974 (Box-folder 12/42)
  - Military, Planes in Vietnam, 1968, undated (Box-folder 12/43)
  - NASA, Academy of Space Scribes, 1975 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - NASA, Accreditation slips, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - NASA, "Aeronautics and Space Report of the President's 1974 Activities" (Box-folder 13/3)
  - NASA, Apollo 7, 1968 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - NASA, Apollo 8, 1968 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - NASA, Apollo 9, 1969 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - NASA, Apollo 11, 1969 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - NASA, Apollo 11, Splashdown Party, 1969 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - NASA, Apollo 13, 1970 (Box-folder 13/9)
  - NASA, Apollo 13, Log Notes, 1970 (Box-folder 13/10)
  - NASA, Apollo 13, USS Iwo Jima, 1970 (Box-folder 13/11)
  - NASA, Apollo 14, 1970 (Box-folder 13/12)
  - NASA, Apollo 14, Science at Fra Mauro, 1970 (Box-folder 13/13)
  - NASA, Apollo 15, At Hadley Base, 1971 (Box-folder 13/14)
  - NASA, Apollo 15, Envelope, 1971 (Box-folder 13/15)
  - NASA, Apollo 16, At Descartes, undated (Box-folder 13/16)
  - NASA, Apollo 17, At Taurus Littrow, undated (Box-folder 13/17)
  - NASA, Apollo 17, Postal Covers, undated (Box-folder 13/18)
  - NASA, "Apollo Expeditions to the Moon", 1976 (Box-folder 13/19)
  - NASA, Apollo Manned Mission Emblems, 1972 (Box-folder 13/20)
  - NASA, Apollo, Soyuz Test Project, 1975 (Box-folder 13/21)
  - NASA, Astronauts Fact Sheet, 1978 (Box-folder 13/22)
  - NASA, Astronaut List of Flights, undated (Box-folder 13/23)
  - NASA, Bahama, undated (Box-folder 13/24)
  - NASA, Cape Canaveral, undated (Box-folder 13/25)
  - NASA, Certificate of Return, 1971 (Box-folder 13/26)
  - NASA, Certificate of Return, 1972 (Box-folder 13/27)
  - NASA, Certificate of Return, 1973 (Box-folder 13/28)
  - NASA, Gemini Song, "On Top of Old Gemini", undated (Box-folder 13/29)
  - NASA, Gemini 3, 1965 (Box-folder 13/30)
  - NASA, Historical Sketch of NASA, 1965, 1969-1970, undated (Box-folder 13/31)
  - NASA, Hubbard Medal to John H. Glenn, Jr., 1962 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - NASA, Lunar Landing, undated (Box-folder 14/2)
  - NASA, Major Launch Record, 1959-1968 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - NASA, "Man on Moon", 1969 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - NASA, Mercury Project, 1963 (Box-folder 14/5)
  - NASA, Mercury Project, 1963 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - NASA, Midget Moons, 1956 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - NASA, Moon Port 1, 1967 (Box-folder 14/8)
  - NASA, NASA News, 1979 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - NASA, Quarantine of Apollo 13, 1970 (Box-folder 14/10)
  - NASA, RCA - Apollos, undated (Box-folder 14/11)
  - NASA, Reception 10 th Anniversary Explorer I, 1968 (Box-folder 14/12)
  - NASA, Results of the First United States Manned Orbital Space Flight, 1962 (Box-folder 14/13)
  - NASA, Results of the 2 nd United States Manned Suborbital Space Flight, 1961 (Box-folder 14/14)
  - NASA, Results of 3 rd United States Manned Orbital Space Flight, 1962 (Box-folder 14/15)
  - NASA, Scientific Satellite Program, Naval Research Lab, 1955, 1071 (Box-folder 14/16)
  - NASA, Scout Launches, 1979 (Box-folder 14/17)
  - NASA, Space Facts, undated (Box-folder 14/18)
  - NASA, Space Flight, 1971 (Box-folder 14/19)
  - NASA, Space Flight, 1969 (Box-folder 14/20)
  - NASA, Space Shuttle, 1979 (Box-folder 14/21)
  - NASA, Splashdowns, 1977 (Box-folder 14/22)
  - NASA, Tiger Times Daily, 1972 (Box-folder 14/23)
  - NASA, USS Boxer, Gemini, 1966 (Box-folder 14/24)
  - NASA, USS Essex, Apollo 7, 1968 (Box-folder 14/25)
  - NASA, USS Okinawa, TOR II Gator, 1971 (Box-folder 14/26)
  - NASA, USS Wasp, Gemini, 1966 (Box-folder 14/27)
  - NASA, Vanguard, 1973 (Box-folder 14/28)
  - NASA, Viking Mars News Conference, 1975 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - NASA, Voyager, 1974 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - ONR Balloon Projects, Cosmic Ray Research Program, 1960 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - Pillsbury, Special Pillsbury Mills Flight, 1953 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Pilot Puppeteer, Jim Gamble, undated (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Rome, Dateline, 1968 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Russia Trip, 1956 (Box-folder 15/7)
  - K'Tut Tantri, Indonesian Independence, 1946-1947, 1949 (Box-folder 15/8)
  - Tess Haugland, West Indies Water-Log, 1953 (Box-folder 15/9)
  - Travel, Bali, undated (Box-folder 15/10)
  - Travel, Guam, undated (Box-folder 15/11)
  - Travel, Hong Kong, undated (Box-folder 15/12)
  - Travel, Honolulu, undated (Box-folder 15/13)
  - Travel, Manila, undated (Box-folder 15/14)
  - Travel, Maps of Micronesia, undated (Box-folder 15/15)
  - Travel, New Zealand, undated (Box-folder 15/16)
  - Travel, Singapore, undated (Box-folder 15/17)
  - Travel, Sydney, undated (Box-folder 15/18)
  - Travel, Tahiti, undated (Box-folder 15/19)
  - Travel, Tokyo, undated (Box-folder 15/20)
- Clippings, 1930-1986; Series VI; 1.25 linear feet
  This series of articles is divided into two subseries: Vern Haugland and Other Authors. Most of the clippings by Haugland are written on the NASA space program, and center on the Apollo missions, missile testing, and army rocket tests. People that Haugland wrote about were Charles Lindbergh, General Douglas MacArthur, and Admiral Richard Byrd. Other topics that he was interested dealt with aviation, including air travel, airports, and different types of aircrafts. The articles written by other authors that Haugland collected dealt with the NASA space program, missile testing, and satellites. Other topics included moon research, the Eagle Squadron, and the Air Force. Articles written about the Haugland family and Haugland himself are also in the series. Many of these articles are about Haugland's time in New Guinea and the book that Haugland wrote about his experiences, his war years, and copies of his obituaries after his death in 1984.
  The series is arranged in two subseries, then alphabetically.
  - Subseries 1: Vern Haugland
    - Admiral Richard Byrd, South Pole, 1971 (Box-folder 15/21)
    - Air Force, 1953, 1956-1958, 1963 (Box-folder 15/22)
    - Air Force, Pilotless Flight, 1954 (Box-folder 15/23)
    - Airlines, 1957, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 15/24)
    - Airports, 1952, 1962, 1972 (Box-folder 15/25)
    - Air Travel, 1967 (Box-folder 15/26)
    - Aleutian Island Volcano, 1948 (Box-folder 15/27)
    - Apollo 7, 1968 (Box-folder 15/28)
    - Apollo 8, 1968 (Box-folder 15/29)
    - Apollo 9, 1969 (Box-folder 15/30)
    - Apollo 13, 1970 (Box-folder 15/31)
    - Apollo 15, 1971 (Box-folder 15/32)
    - Apoll 17, 1972 (Box-folder 15/33)
    - Apollo Moon Landing Sites, undated (Box-folder 15/34)
    - Army Rocket Tests, 1958 (Box-folder 15/35)
    - Articles written in Foreign Languages, 1953-1966 (Box-folder 15/36)
    - Auto Train, 1972 (Box-folder 15/37)
    - Aviation, 1951, and undated (Box-folder 15/38)
    - Civil Aernonautics Board, 1972 (Box-folder 15/39)
    - Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962 (Box-folder 15/40)
    - Jimmy Doolittle Headlines, 1959, 1971 (Box-folder 15/41)
    - Gemini 3, 1965 (Box-folder 16/1)
    - Kennedy Family Plane, 1962 (Box-folder 16/2)
    - General Curtis LeMay, 1955, 1957, 1965 (Box-folder 16/3)
    - Charles Lindbergh, 1954, and undated (Box-folder 16/4)
    - General Douglas MacArthur, 1943, 1964 (Box-folder 16/5)
    - Military Aircrafts, 1953-1958, 1973 (Box-folder 16/6)
    - Missile Tests, 1952, 1958 (Box-folder 16/7)
    - NASA, 1958-1959, 1962, undated (Box-folder 16/8)
    - Skylab, 1974 (Box-folder 16/9)
    - Soviet Union, undated (Box-folder 16/10)
    - Tourism, 1973 (Box-folder 16/11)
    - USS Enterprise, 1962 (Box-folder 16/12)
    - USS Superlative, undated (Box-folder 16/13)
  - Subseries 2: Other Authors
    - Aircraft, undated (Box-folder 16/14)
    - Air Force Awards, 1955 (Box-folder 16/15)
    - Airports, 1977, undated (Box-folder 16/16)
    - Apollo 11, 1969 (Box-folder 16/17)
    - Apollo 13, 1970 (Box-folder 16/18)
    - Apollo/Soyuz Mission, 1972, 1975, 1977 (Box-folder 16/19)
    - Associated Press News, 1944 (Box-folder 16/20)
    - Eagle Squadron, 1979, 1983 (Box-folder 16/21)
    - Haugland's Awards, 1942-1977 (Box-folder 16/22)
    - Haugland's Biographical Information, 1977, 1979, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 16/23)
    - Haugland's Book Reviews, 1943, 1948, 1979 (Box-folder 16/24)
    - Haugland Family Articles, 1939-1986 (Box-folder 16/25)
    - Haugland and New Guinea, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 16/26)
    - Haugland Obituaries, 1984 (Box-folder 16/27)
    - Haugland Returns from WWII, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 16/28)
    - Haugland and work, 1943-1969 (Box-folder 16/29)
    - Japan, undated (Box-folder 16/30)
    - K'Tut Tantri, 1947-1952 (Box-folder 16/31)
    - Charles Lindbergh, 1974 (Box-folder 16/32)
    - W.J. McMahon, undated (Box-folder 16/33)
    - Missile Testing, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 16/34)
    - Montana, 1936 (Box-folder 16/35)
    - Moon Research, 1974 (Box-folder 16/36)
    - Newspaper Story Competition, 1977 (Box-folder 16/37)
    - Richard Nixon, 1977 (Box-folder 16/38)
    - Pilots, undated (Box-folder 16/39)
    - Satellites, 1957-1958, 1960 (Box-folder 17/1)
    - Scrapbook, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 17/2)
    - Scrapbook, Haugland in Pacific, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 17/3)
    - Skylab, 1974 (Box-folder 17/4)
    - Space Program, 1974 (Box-folder 17/5)
    - Space Shuttle, 1974 (Box-folder 17/6)
    - USS New Orleans, 1975 (Box-folder 17/7)
    - USS Okinawa, undated (Box-folder 17/8)
    - World War II, 1945, 1953, undated (Box-folder 17/9)
- Personal, 1908-1987; Series VII; 1.25 linear feet
  This series consists of booklets and pamphlets from many of Haugland's memberships, including the Aviation Writers Association and the National Aeronautic Association. His work journals are also included in the series, and many are written in shorthand. Haugland kept travel receipts and memorabilia from the Pacific island and Soviet Union trips that he took while working for the Associated Press. He received many certificates and citations, such as honorary memberships from the many ships that he traveled on while covering the NASA splashdowns and awards from writing associations. Correspondence with his wife, Tess, and his daughters is also in the series. There is also biographical information on Haugland in the series. A WWII based novel is also included within the series. This book deals with the war's 100 most fascinating stories. Haugland's story about his ordeal in New Guinea is included in the book.
  - Air Force, 1953, 1958-1960, 1963 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - American Newspaper Guild Manual, 1947 (Box-folder 18/2)
  - Apollo 15 Press Passes, 1971 (Box-folder 18/3)
  - Army/Navy Press Weekend Guest List, 1969 (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Associated Press Retirement Antidotes, 1973 (Box-folder 18/5)
  - Associated Press Correspondents Pamphlet, undated (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Autographed Song Booklet, "The Aussies and the Yanks are Here," Johnny Nauer, 1952 (Box-folder 18/7)
  - Aviation Writers Association, 1959-1987 (Box-folder 18/8)
  - Biographical Information, 1955, 1982 (Box-folder 18/9)
  - The Catholic Hour Pamphlet, 1942 (Box-folder 18/10)
  - Certificates and Citations, 1929-1982 (Box-folder 18/11)
  - Certificates and Citations, 1947-1979 (Box-folder OS 1/3)
  - Christmas Gifts Received, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 18/12)
  - Copyright Law Pamphlets, 1980 (Box-folder 18/13)
  - Correspondence with Daughters, 1959-1973 (Box-folder 18/14)
  - Correspondence with Family, 1945, 1955, 1982 (Box-folder 18/15)
  - Correspondence with Tess, 1942-1974 (Box-folder 18/16)
  - Datebook, 1950 (Box-folder 18/17)
  - Drawings from daughters, undated (Box-folder 18/18)
  - Eagle Squadron Copyright Laws, 1986 (Box-folder 18/19)
  - The Eagles' War Book Cover, undated (Box-folder 18/20)
  - "Face the Nation" Broadcast, 1959 (Box-folder 18/21)
  - The First Flight Society, 1967 (Box-folder 18/22)
  - Greenland History, undated (Box-folder 18/23)
  - Haugland Family, 1972, 1979 (Box-folder 18/24)
  - Haugland Pacific Trip, 1973 (Box-folder 18/25)
  - Haugland Staionary, undated (Box-folder 18/26)
  - Virginia Hewlett, 1967 (Box-folder 18/27)
  - International Vaccination Cards, 1955-1957, 1973 (Box-folder 18/28)
  - Interviews, 1943, 1945 (Box-folder 18/29)
  - Joke Subpoena, 1970 (Box-folder 18/30)
  - Work Journal, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 18/31)
  - Work Journal, 1955 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Work Journal, 1966 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Work Journals, 1974, 1976-1977, 1979 (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Work Journal, 1981 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Life, Pictorial Histories of 1940s, 1950s and 1960s, 1987 (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Tex McCrary, 1973 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - William J. McMahon Memorial, 1963 (Box-folder 19/7)
  - Membership and Business Cards, 1943-1985 (Box-folder 19/8)
  - Montanan, 1985 (Box-folder 19/9)
  - Music Scores, 1908, undated (Box-folder 19/10)
  - National Aeronautic Association Booklets, 1969, 1972 (Box-folder 19/11)
  - John O'Donnell, 1948 (Box-folder 19/12)
  - Official Program Mock-ups for Eagles '50s Reunion, 1979 (Box-folder 19/13)
  - Phi-Life Edition Newsletter, 1943 (Box-folder 19/14)
  - Poem, "Wall of Andrus", 1968 (Box-folder 19/15)
  - Press Releases of Awards, 1956, 1976, undated (Box-folder 19/16)
  - Professional Aerospace Communicators Newsletter, 1978 (Box-folder 19/17)
  - Russian Trip, 1959 (Box-folder 19/18)
  - Saga Samurai Ace, Fred Saito, undated (Box-folder 19/19)
  - State University of Montana Diploma, 1931 (Box-folder 19/20)
  - Paul Thayer, 1975 (Box-folder 19/21)
  - Title suggestions for Lost in New Guinea, 1942 (Box-folder 19/22)
  - University of Montana 50th Reunion, 1981 (Box-folder 19/23)
  - Robert Vote, 1979 (Box-folder 19/24)
  - Wartime Releases, 1943 (Box-folder 19/25)
  - "The Whimper," Dale Smith, undated (Box-folder 19/26)
  - White House Correspondents' Association, 1953, 1973 (Box-folder 19/27)
  - Encyclopedia Year Book 1972, Grolier Incorporated (Box-folder 20/1)
  - The 100 Best True Stories of World War II, Wm. H. Wise & Co., Inc., 1945 (Box-folder 20/2)
- Memorabilia, 1942-1978 and undated; Series VIII; 2 linear feet
  This series contains artifacts that Haugland collected during his years with the Associated Press. Many of the artifacts relate to aviation, such as a wing remnant from the New Orleans first round-the-world flight in 1924 and a plaque commemorating the first flight by the Wright brothers in 1903. Other memorabilia centers on the NASA space program, mainly the Apollo missions. Also in the series are artifacts dedicated to Haugland on the numerous awards that he received. He received the Associated Press Medal of Honor, the Associated Press Strebig-Dobben Memorial Award, the Air Force Association Arts and Letter Award. Haugland also received an airplane propeller in 1973 signed by his friends in aviation.
  - Air Force Association Arts and Letters Award Trophy, 1955 (Box 21)
  - Golden Gate Bridge Original Suspender Cable Segment, cut, 1975 (Box 21)
  - The Lauren D. Lyman Award, for aviation writing, 1976 (Box 21)
  - Leather Bookmark from Denmark (Box 21)
  - Luggage Tag, Master Navigator, undated (Box 21)